<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charter of Mary-land.</title>
            <title>Charter</title>
            <author>Maryland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09480</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80923065</idno>
  <idno type="VID">191916</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248550089</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80923065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220786</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">80923065</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09480)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2895:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charter of Mary-land.</title>
                  <title>Charter</title>
                  <author>Maryland.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"... [A]t Westminster, the twentith [sic] day of June, in the eighth year of Our reign"--P. 23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Maryland --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="charter">
            <pb facs="tcp:191916:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191916:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191916:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>English coat of arms, circa 1632</figDesc>
                  <p>C R</p>
                  <p>HONI· SOIT· QVI· MAL· Y· PENSE</p>
                  <p>DIEV· ET MON· DROIT</p>
               </figure>THE CHARTER OF <hi>MARY-LAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES By the Grace of God, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To all to whom these Presents shall come greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas our right Trusty and wellbeloved Subject, <hi>Cecilius Calvert,</hi> Baron of <hi>Baltemore</hi> in our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Son &amp; Heir of Sir <hi>George Calvert</hi> Knight, late Baron of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore</hi> in the same Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191916:3"/> his Fathers Intentions, being excited with a laudable and pious Zeal for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Christian Faith, &amp; the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of our Empire and Dominion, hath humbly besought leave of Us, by his Industry and charge, to transport an ample Colony of the <hi>English</hi> Nation unto a certain Country hereafter described, in the Parts of <hi>America,</hi> not yet cultivated &amp; planted, tho' in some Parts thereof inhabited by certain barbarous People, having no Knowledge of Almighty God, and hath humbly besought our Royal Majesty to give, grant, and confirm all the said Country, with certain Priviledges and Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, requisit for the good Government, and State of his Colony, and Country afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, to him and his Heirs for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Bounds.</note>Know ye therefore, that We favouring the pious and Noble Purpose of the said Barons of <hi>Baltemore,</hi> of our special Grace, certain Knowledge, and meer Motion, have given, granted, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and by this our present Charter, for Us, our Heirs, and Successors, do give, grant, and confirm unto the said <hi>Cecilius,</hi> now Baron of <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, all that Part of a <hi>Peninsula,</hi> lying in the parts of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> between the Ocean on the East, and the Bay of <hi>Chesopeack</hi> on the West, &amp; divided from the other part thereof, by a right line drawn
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191916:3"/> from the Promontory or Cape of Land called <hi>Watkins Point</hi> (situate in the foresaid Bay, near the River of <hi>Wighco</hi>) on the West, unto the main Ocean on the East; and between that bound on the South, unto that part of <hi>Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware</hi> bay on the North, which lieth under the Fortieth Degree of Northerly Latitude from the Equinoctial, where <hi>New-England</hi> ends: And all that tract of land between the bounds aforesaid, that is to say, passing from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said bay, called <hi>Deleware</hi> bay, in a right line by the Degree aforesaid, unto the true Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the first Fountain of the River <hi>Pattow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meck,</hi> and from thence trending toward the South unto the farther bank of the foresaid River, &amp; following the West and South Side thereof unto a certain Place called <hi>Cinquack</hi> situate near the Mouth of the said river, where it falls into the bay of <hi>Chesopeack,</hi> and from thence by a strait line unto the foresaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montory, and Place called <hi>Watkins Point</hi> (so that all that tract of land divided by the line aforesaid, drawn between the main Ocean and <hi>Watkins Point,</hi> unto the Promontory cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cape Charles,</hi> &amp; all its Appurtenances, do remain intirely excepted to us, our Heirs, and Successors for ever.)</p>
            <p>We do also grant and confirm unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, all Islands, and Ilets within the Limits aforesaid,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191916:4"/> and all and singular the Islands and Ilets, which are, or shall be in the Ocean, within 10 leagues from the Eastern Shore of the said Country, towards the East, with all and singular Ports, Harbours, bays, Rivers, and Inlets, belonging unto the Country, or Islands aforesaid: And all the Soile, Lands, Fields, Woods, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Fenns, Lakes, Rivers, Bays and Inlets, situate, or being within the bounds, and limits aforesaid, with the fishing of all Sorts of Fish <hi>Whales, Sturgeons,</hi> &amp; all other royal Fishes in the Sea, bays, Inlets or Rivers, within the Premises: &amp; the Fish therein taken: &amp; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over all Veins, Mines, and Quarries, as well discovered, as not discovered, of Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Gems, and precious Stones, and all other whatsoever, be it of Stones, Mettals, or of any other thing, or Matter whatsoever, found or to be found, within the Country, Isles, &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits aforesaid. And furthermore the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages and Advowsons of all Churches, which (as Christian Religion shall encrease within the Countrey, Isles, Ilets, and limits aforesaid) shall happen hereafter to be erected: together with licence and power, to build &amp; found Churches, Chappels, &amp; Oratories, in conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; fit places within the premises, and to cause them to be dedicated, and consecrated according to the Ecclesiastical Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Kingdom of <hi>England: together with</hi> all &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191916:4"/> the like, and as ample Rights, Jurisdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Priviledges, Prerogatives, Royalties, Liberties, Immunities, Royal rights and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises of what kind soever temporal, as well by Sea, as by Land, within the Country, Isles, Ilets, and limits aforesaid; to have, exercise, use and enjoy the same, as amply as any Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jurisdiction of a Count <hi>Palatine</hi>
               </note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bishoprick, or County <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> in our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> hath at any Time heretofore had, held, used, or enjoyed, or of Right ought, or might have had, held, used, or enjoyed.</p>
            <p>And him the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, we do by these Presents for Us, Our Heirs and Successors, make, create, and constitute the true and absolute Lords, &amp; Proprietaries of the Country aforesaid, and of all other the Premises, (except before excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) saving always, the Faith and Allegiance, and Sovereign Dominion due unto Us, Our Heirs and Successors.</p>
            <p>To have, hold, possess, and enjoy the said Country, Isles, Ilets, and other the Premises, unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltimore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, to the sole and proper use and behoof of him the said now Lord <hi>Baltimore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns for ever.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:191916:5"/>
            <p>To be holden of us, our Heirs, and Successors,<note place="margin">Tenure.</note> Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as of our Castle of <hi>Windsor,</hi> in our County of <hi>Berkshire,</hi> in free and common soc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage, by Fealty only, for all Services, &amp; not <hi>in Capite,</hi> or by Knights Service: Yielding &amp; paying therefore to us, our Heirs and Successors,<note place="margin">Rent.</note> two <hi>Indian</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of those Parts, to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at our said Castle of <hi>Windsor,</hi> every Year, on the Tuesday in <hi>Easter</hi> Week; and also the fifth Part of all Gold and Silver Oare within the limits aforesaid, which shall from Time to Time happen to be found.</p>
            <p>Now that the said Country thus by us Granted and Described, may be Eminent above all other parts of the said Territory, and dignified with larger Titles: Know ye that we of our farther Grace, certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and meer Motion, have thought fit to erect the same Country and Islands into a Province, as out of the Fullness of our Royal Power, and Prerogative, we do for Us, our Heirs, and Successors, erect, and incorporate them into a Province, and do call it <hi>Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp; so from henceforth will have it called.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as we have hereby made and ordained the foresaid now Lord <hi>Balti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> the true Lord, and Proprietary of all the Province aforesaid: Know ye therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191916:5"/> moreover, that we, reposing especial Trust &amp; Confidence in the Fidelity, Wisdom, Justice, and provident Circumspection of the said now Lord <hi>Baltimore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Power to enact Laws</note> for Us, our Heirs and Successors, do grant free, full, and absolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by Vertue of these presents, to him, and his Heirs, for the good &amp; happy Government of the said Province, to ordain, make, enact and under his and their Seals to publish any Laws whatsoever, appertaining either unto the publick State of the said Province or unto the private Utility of particular Persons, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto their best Discretions, of and with the Advise, Assent and Approbation of the Free-men of the said Province, or the greater Part of them, or of their Delegates or Deputies, whom for the enacting of the faid Laws, when, and as often as need shall require, we will that the said now Lord <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timore,</hi> and his Heirs, shall affemble in such Sort and Form as to him or them shall seem best: And the same Laws duly to execute up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all People, within the said Province, and limits thereof, for the Time being, or that shall be constituted under the Government, and Power of him or them, either sailing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Mary-land,</hi> or returning from thence toward <hi>England,</hi> or any other of ours, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Dominions, by Imposition of Penalties,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191916:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:191916:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191916:7"/> Imprisonment, or any other Punishment; yea is it shall be needful, &amp; that the quality of the Offence require it, by taking away mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or life, either by him the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> &amp; his Heirs, or by his or their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, Lieutenants, Judges, Justices, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, Officers, and Ministers, to be ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or appointed, according to the Tenor and true Intention of these Presents: And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to appoint and establish any Judges &amp; Justices, Magistrates and Officers, whatsoever, at Sea and Land, for what Cause soever, and with what power soever, and in such form, as to the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> or his Heirs shall seems most convenient! Also to remit, release, pardon and abolish, whether before Judgment, or after, all Crimes or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences whatsoever, against the said Laws: &amp; to do all and every other thing or things, which unto the compleat Establishment of Justice, unto Courts, Praetories, and Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, forms of Judicature, &amp; manners of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding do belong: Altho' in these Presents, express Mention be not made thereof, &amp; by Judges by them delegated, to award Process, hold Pleas, &amp; determine in all the said courts &amp; Tribunals, all Actions, suits, and Causes whatsoever as well criminal, as civil, perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, real, mixt and praetorial; which laws, so as afore said to be published, Our Pleasure is,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191916:7"/> &amp; so we enjoin, require, and command, shall be most absolute &amp; available in Law, &amp; that all the Liege-People, and subjects of us, our Heirs and Successors, do observe &amp; keep the same inviolably, in those parts, so far as they concern them, under the pains therein expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, or to be expressed: Provided neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, that the said laws be consonant to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and be not repugnant or contrary, but as near as conveniently may be, agreeable to the laws, Statutes, Customs and rights of this Our Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And forasmuch, as in the Government of so great a Province, sudden Accidents do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happen, whereunto it will be necessary to apply a Remedy, before the Freeholders of the said Province, their Delegates, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, can be assembled to the making of laws, neither will it be convenient, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly upon every such emergent Occasion so great a Multitude should be called together, therefore for the better Government of the said Province, we will and ordain, &amp; by these presents for us, our Heirs &amp; Successors, do grant unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> and his heirs, that the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> &amp; his heirs, by themselves, or by their Magis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates and Officers in that Behalf duely to be ordained as aforesaid, may make and constitute, fit and wholesome Ordinances, from Time to Time, within the said Province, to be kept
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191916:8"/> &amp; observed, as well for the Preservation of the Peace, as for the better Government of the People there inhabiting, and publickly to notify the same to all Persons, whom the same doth, or any Way may concern; which Ordinances, Our Pleasure is, shall be observed inviolably within the said Province, under the pains therein to be expressed. So as the said Ordinances be consonant to reason, &amp; be not repugnant nor contrary, but so far as conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently may be, agreeable with the Laws and Statutes of our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and so as the said Ordinances be not extended, in any Sort to bind, charge, or take away the right or Interest of any Person, or Persons, of, or in their Life, Member, Freehold, Goods, or Chattels.</p>
            <p>Furthermore that this new Colony may the more happily encrease by the Multitude of People resorting thither,<note place="margin">Licence to go to <hi>Mary-land.</hi>
               </note> &amp; may likewise be the more strongly defended from the Incursions of Salvages, or other Enemies, Pyrates, and Robbers: Therefore we, for us, our Heirs and Successors, do give and grant by these Presents, power, Licence and Liberty unto all the liege-People, &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, both present and future, of us, our heirs, &amp; Successors (excepting those who shall be specially forbidden) to transport themselves
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191916:8"/> &amp; Familys unto the said Province, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient shipping and fitting Provisions, and there to settle themselves, dwell and inhabit, and to build, and fortify Castles, Forts, and other Places of Strength, for the publick, and their own private Defence, at the Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> &amp; his Heirs, the Statute of Fugitives▪ or any other whatsoever, the contrary of the Premises, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And we will also, and of our more special Grace, for us, our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, we do straightly enjoin,<note place="margin">People born in <hi>Maryland</hi> made Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> constitute, ordain, and command that the said Province shall be of our Allegiance, and that all and singular the Subjects and Liege-people of us, our Heirs and Successors, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, or to be transported into the said Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and the Children of them, and of such as shall descend from them, there already born, or hereafter to be born, be, and shall be Denizens and Lieges of us, our Heirs, and Successors, of our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and be in all Things held, treated, reputed and esteemed as the liege faithfull People of us, our Heirs and Successors, born within our Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> &amp; likewise any Lands, Tenements, Revenues, Services, and other Hereditaments whatsoever, within
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191916:9"/> our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and other our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, may inherit, or otherwise purchase, receive, take, have, hold, buy, &amp; possess, &amp; them may occupy, &amp; enjoy, give, sell, aliene, and bequeath, as likewise, all Liberties, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises, and Priviledges, of this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> freely, quietly, and peaceably, have &amp; possess, occupy and enjoy, as our liege people, born, or to be born, within our said Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> without the let, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestation, vexation, trouble or Grievance, of us, our Heirs, and Successors: Any Statute, Act, Ordinance, or Provision to the contrary thereof not withstanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, that our Subjects may be the rather encouraged to undertake this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, with ready and chearfull Minds; know ye, that we of our special Grace, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Knowledge, and meer Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Licence to transport goods and merchandise.</note> do give &amp; grant, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of these presents, as well unto the said now Lord <hi>Balte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> and his Heirs, as to all other that shall from Time to Time repair unto that Province, with a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to inhabit there, or to trade with the Natives of the said Province, full License to lade and fraight in any Ports whatsoever, of us, our Heirs and Successors, and into the said Province of <hi>Mary land,</hi> by them, their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191916:9"/> Servants or Assigns, to transport, all and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, their Goods, Wares, and Merchandise; as likewise all sorts of Grain whatsoever and any other things whatsoever, necessary for Food or Clothing (not prohibited by the laws and Statutes of our Kingdoms and Dominions to be carried out of the said Kingdoms) without any let, or Molestation of us, our Heirs, or Successors, or of any of the Officers of us, our Heirs or Successors; (saving always to us, our Heirs and Successors, the Impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Customs, and other duties and payments for the said Wares, and Merchandise) any Statute, Act, Ordinance or other thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And because in so remote a Country, &amp; si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate amongst so many barbarous nations, the Incursion as well of the Salvages themselves, as of other <hi>Enemies, Pyrates,</hi> &amp; <hi>Robbers,</hi> may probably be feared:<note place="margin">Power of War and peace.</note> Therefore we have given, &amp; for us, our Heirs, and Successors, do give Power by these Presents, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs, or As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, by themselves, or their Captains, or other their Officers, to leavy, muster and train, all Sorts of Men, of what Condition or where so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever born, in the said Province of <hi>Mary-land</hi> for the time being, and to make War, and to pursue, the <hi>Enemies</hi> and <hi>Robbers</hi> aforesaid,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191916:10"/> as well by Sea as by Land, yea, even without the limits of the said Province, and (by Gods Assistance) to vanquish &amp; take them, &amp; being taken, to put them to Death by the Law of War, or to save them at their Pleasure, &amp; to do all and every other thing which unto the Charge and Office of a Captain General of an Army belongeth, or hath accustomed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, as fully and freely, as any Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of an Army, hath ever had the same.</p>
            <p>Also our Will and Pleasure is, and by this our Charter,<note place="margin">Mart. Law</note> We do give unto the said now Lord <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore,</hi> his Heirs, and Assigns, full <hi>Power, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> &amp; <hi>Authority,</hi> in Case of <hi>Rebellion, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> if any should happen, (which God forbid) either upon the Land within the <hi>Province</hi> aforesaid, or upon the <hi>Main Sea,</hi> in making a Voyage thither, or returning from thence, by themselves, or their <hi>Captains, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties,</hi> or other Officers, to be authorized un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Seals for that Purpose (to whom we also, for us, our Heirs and Successors, do give and grant by these Presents, full Power and Authority) to exercise Martial Law against mutinous and seditious persons of those parts, such as shall refuse to submit themselves, to his, or their Government, or shall refuse to serve in the Wars, or shall fly to the Enemy or forsake their Ensigns, or be Loyterers, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:191916:10"/> Straglers, or otherwise however offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Law, Custom, and Discipline Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, as freely, and in as ample Manner and Form, as any Captain general of an Army by vertue of his Office, might, or hath, accustom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to use the same.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, that the Way to Honours &amp; Dignities,<note place="margin">Power to confer Honour</note> may not seem to be altogether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and shut up, to Men well born, &amp; such as shall prepare themselves unto this present Plantation, and shall desire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deserve well of us, &amp; our Kingdoms, both in Peace and War, in so far distant &amp; remote a Country: Therefore we, for us, our Heirs, and Successors, do give free, and absolute Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, to confer favours, rewards, and Honours, upon such Inhabitants within the Province aforesaid, as shall deserve the same; &amp; to invest them, with what Titles &amp; Dignities soever, as he shall think fit, (so as they be not such as are now used in <hi>England</hi>) As likewise to erect and incorporate, Towns into Boroughs, &amp; Boroughs into Cities, with convenient Priviledges and Immunities, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Merit of the Inhabitants, and fitness of the Places, and to do all and every other thing or things, touching the Premises, which to him, or them, shall seem meet and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:191916:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:191916:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:191916:12"/> requsite; albeit they be such as of their own Nature might otherwise require a more speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Commandment and Warrant, than in these Presents is expressed.</p>
            <p>We will also, and by these Presents, for us, our Heirs and Successors, we do give &amp; grant License, by this our Charter, unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, &amp; to all the Inhabitants and Dwellers in the said Province aforesaid, both present and to come, to import, or unlade, by themselves, or their Servants, Factors, or Assigns, all Merchandises &amp; Goods whatsoever, that shall arise of the Fruits and Commodities of the said province, either by Land or Sea, into any of the Ports of us, our Heirs and Successors, in our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> or otherwise to dispose of the said Goods, in the said Ports, &amp; if need be, within one year next after the unlading of the same, to lade the said Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandises and Goods again, into the same or other Ships, and to export the same into any other Countrys, either of our Dominion or forreign, (being in Amity with us, our Heirs, and Successors) provided always that they pay such Customs, Impositions, Subsidies &amp; Duties for the same, to us, our Heirs and Successors, as the rest of our Subjects of our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> for the Time being, shall be bound to pay: Beyond which we will not that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191916:12"/> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the foresaid Province of <hi>Mary-land</hi> shall be any way charged.</p>
            <p>And furthermore of our more ample and special grace, certain knowledge &amp; meer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we do, for us, our Heirs, and Successors, grant unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his <hi>Heirs</hi> &amp; <hi>Assigns</hi> full and absolute Power and Authority, to make, erect, and constitute, within the Province of <hi>Mary-land,</hi> and the Isles and Ilets aforesaid, such, &amp; so many Sea-ports, Harbours, Creeks and other Places for discharge &amp; unlading of goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dises, out of Ships, Boats, and other vessels, &amp; lading them, and in such and so many Places, and with such Rights, Jurisdictions, Liberties and Priviledges, unto the said ports belonging as to him or them shall seem most expedient. And that all and singular the Ships boats, and other Vessels, which shall come for Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise and trade unto the said Province, or out of the same shall depart; shall be laden and unladen only at such Ports as shall be so erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and constituted by the said now Lord <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore,</hi> his heirs or Assigns, any Use, Custom, or other thing to the contrary notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; saving always unto us, our Heirs &amp; suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, and to all the Subjects (of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi>) of us, our heirs and successors, free liberty of fishing for Sea fish, as well in the Sea, Bays, Inlets, &amp; navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Rivers, as in the Harbours, Bays, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191916:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:191916:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:191916:14"/> Creeks of the Province aforesaid, &amp; the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of salting and drying their fish on the Shore of the said Province, &amp; for the same cause, to cut and take underwood, or twiggs there growing, &amp; to build Cottages &amp; shedds necessary in this behalf, as they heretofore have, or might reasonably have used, which Liberties &amp; Priviiedges, nevertheless, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects aforesaid, of us, our Heirs and Successors, shall enjoy without any notable dammage, or Injury to be done, to the said now Lord <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore,</hi> his Heirs or assigns or to the Dwellers and Inhabitants of the said Province, in the ports, Creeks and Shores aforesaid, &amp; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the Woods and Copses growing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the said Province: And if any shall do any such dammage or Injury, he shall incurr the heavy Displeasure of us, our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, the Punishment of the Laws; &amp; shall moreover make Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>We do furthermore will, appoint &amp; ordain and by these Presents, for us, our Heirs and Successors, we do grant unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs and assigns, that he the said Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs and assigns may from time to time for ever, have and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, the Customs and Subsidies, in the ports, Harbours, and other Creeks and places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, within the province aforesaid; payable, or due for Merchandises and Wares, there to be laded or unladed, the said Customs &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191916:14"/> to be reasonably assessed (upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion) by themselves &amp; the People there, as aforesaid; to whom we give Power by these Presents, for us, our Heirs and Successors up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on just Cause, and in a due Proportion, to assess and impose the same.</p>
            <p>And further, of our special grace, and of our certain knowledge, and meer motion, we have, given, granted &amp; confirmed, &amp; by these Presents for us, our heirs and Successors, do give, grant &amp; confirm unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs and assigns▪ full and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute License, power and authority, that he the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs &amp; As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, from time to time hereafter for ever, at his, or their will &amp; pleasure, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y assign, alien grant, demise, or enfeoff, of the premises so many, &amp; such parts and parcels, to him, or them, that shall be willing to purchase the same, as they shall think fit, to have &amp; to hold to them the said person or persons, willing to take or purchase the same, their Heirs &amp; As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, in fee simple, or fee tail, or for term of Life, or Lives or years, to be held of the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs, and assigns by such services, customs and rents, as shall seem fit to the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns; and not immediately of us our heirs, or Successors: &amp; to the same person or persons, &amp; to all and every of them, we do give, and grant by these presents for us, our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191916:15"/> heirs, and Successors, license, authority and power, that such Person or Persons, may take the Premises, or any Parcel thereof, of the fore said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs or assigns and the same hold to themselves, their heirs, or assigns (in what estate of Inheritance soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in fee simple, or in fee tail, or otherwise, as to them, &amp; the now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs and assigns, shall seem expedient) of the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his heirs &amp; assigns, the Statute made in the Parliament of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> Son of King <hi>Henry,</hi> late King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> our Predecessor, commonly called the S atute <hi>Quia emptores terrarum,</hi> lately publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or any other Statute, Act Ordinance, Use, Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, or any other thing, cause, or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er, thereupon heretofore had, done, published, ordained, or provided to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding; and by these presents we give, &amp; grant▪ license unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> and his heirs, to erect any Parcels of Land within the Province aforesaid into Mannors, &amp; in every of the said Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to have, and to hold a <hi>Court Baron,</hi> with all things whatsoever, which to a <hi>Court Baron</hi> do belong, &amp; to have &amp; hold View of <hi>Franck-Pledge,</hi> (for the Conservation of the Peace, &amp; the better Government of those parts) by themselves, or their Stewards, or by the Lords for the time being of other Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191916:15"/> to be deputed, when they shall be erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and in the same, to use all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>View of Franck-Pledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, our pleasure is, and by these Presents for us, our Heirs, and Successors, we do covenant and grant to and with the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns; That we, our <hi>Heirs</hi> &amp; <hi>Successors,</hi> shall at no time hereafter, set, or make, or cause to be set, any Imposition, Custom, or other Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Rate, or Contribution whatsoever, in or upon the dwellers &amp; Inhabitants of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said province, for their <hi>Lands, Tenements, Goods</hi> or <hi>Chattels</hi> within the said Province, or in or upon any <hi>Goods</hi> or <hi>Merchandises,</hi> within the said Province, or to be lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, or unladen within any the Ports or Harbours of the said Province: And our pleasure is, and for us, our Heirs, and Successors, we charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that this our Declaration shall be henceforward from time to time received, &amp; allowed in all our Courts, and before all the Judges of us, our <hi>Heirs</hi> and <hi>Successors,</hi> for a sufficient &amp; lawful discharge, payment, and acquittance: Commanding all and singular, our Officers and Ministers of us, our Heirs, &amp; Successors, and enjoyning them upon pain of our high Displeasure, that they do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume at any time to attempt any thing to the contrary of the premises, or that they do in any sort withstand the same, but that they be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191916:16"/> at all times aiding and assisting, as is fitting, unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> and his <hi>Heirs,</hi> and to the Inhabitants, and Merchants of <hi>Mary-land</hi> aforesaid, their <hi>Servants, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, Factors</hi> and <hi>Assigns,</hi> in the full use and fruition of the benefit of this our Charter.</p>
            <p>And further our pleasure is, and by these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents for us our Heirs and Successors, we do grant unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns, and to the Tenants and Inhabitants of the said Province of <hi>Mary-land,</hi> both present, and to come, and to every of them, that the said Province, Tenants, and Inhabitants of the said <hi>Colony</hi> or <hi>Countrey,</hi> shall not from henceforth be held or reputed as a member, or a part of the land of <hi>Virginia,</hi> or of any other Colony whatsoever, now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sported, or hereafter to be transported, nor shall be depending on, or subject to their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in any thing, from whom We do separate that, and them, and Our pleasure is, by these Presents that they be separated, and that they be subject immediately to Our Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as depending thereof for ever.</p>
            <p>And If Perchance hereafter it should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that any doubts or questions should arise, concerning the true sence &amp; understanding of any <hi>word, clause,</hi> or <hi>sentence</hi> contained in this our present Charter, We will, ordain, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that at all times, &amp; in all things, such
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191916:16"/> Interpretation be made there of, &amp; allowed in any of Our Courts whatsoever, as shall be judged most advantagious, and favourable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns. Provided always, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be admitted thereof, by which Gods Holy and Truly Christian Religion, or the allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance due unto Us, Our Heirs and Successors, may in any thing suffer any prejudice, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution.</p>
            <p>Although express mention be not made in these Presents, of the true y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rly value, or certainty of the premises, or of any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or of other gifts and grants, made by Us, Our Heirs, and Predecessors▪ unto the said now Lord <hi>Baltemore,</hi> or any S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>te, Act, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, Provision, Proclamation or restraint heretofore had, mnde, published, ordained, or provided, or any other thing, cause, or matter whatsoever to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>In Witness whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Pattents, Witness Our self at <hi>Westminster,</hi> the Twentith day of <hi>June,</hi> In the Eighth Year of Our Reign.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:191916:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191916:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>